Fran: I think naming things with
young people is really important.
I think there's this tendency when
it's mental health to be like, to
sort of, work around what you're
trying to say and not say the words.
And, you know, obviously we deal
with a lot of young people who
are having suicidal feelings
or they were self-harming.
And I think there's a tendency in
parents and a tendency in friends and
to be like, "oh, I don't want to say
the word suicide because it might,
it might make them think about it".
Or "I don't want to say self-harm, you
know, I want to say it in some other way".
And I think as workers, we can
struggle with that sometimes as well.
You know, I was talking to a 14 year
old, like yesterday, who's told me
he's having suicidal feelings, but
there's even this thing in me when
I'm talking to him, that I don't want
to say the word suicide sometimes.
But I thinks that's, that's not helpful.
And I think to not name things and
to just be like working around it
means that you're not actually being
direct with the young person and I
think they want to feel understood.
And I think they want to
have those things named.
A young person feeling like maybe
you're not listening if you're not
repeating those things back with them.
If they're saying "I'm feeling suicidal"
and you'll say then saying, "oh, I know
you feel down sometimes" then I think
that it can be that sort of thing of
"well, I'm not telling you I'm down.
I'm telling you I'm suicidal.
So are you're listening to me?"
And I think it's it's the same
of anxiety and depression.
So I think sometimes we just
don't name those things.
I also think a really important
thing about approaching mental
health of young people is to be a
bit honest about your own situation.
I think as a therapist is that there's
sort of a few schools of thought, and
some people think, "oh, you should
keep your, your sort of background and
your experiences totally out of it".
I don't really agree with that.
I think it's, I think obviously
you've gotta be careful, you
don't want to overshare things.
You don't want to go into a lot of detail,
but I think for a young person to know
that I had anxiety or I still have anxiety
sometimes, I think that can make them feel
really a bit safe in, in the conversation
they're having, and also a bit, cause
I think they look at professionals and
parents as people who have got everything
sorted when they're young and then to
hear, "oh no, we're all, we all struggle
with this stuff",  sometimes I think
can be really, really freeing for them.